Hey, hey, what's up, my friend? So, in
today's video, you will learn a trend
following system that has generated
2,864%
over the last 25 years. This trading
system has about a 14% annual return
and a maximum drawdown of 37%. In other
words, compared to a buy and hold on the
S&P 500, this system has
higher returns and lower risk. And the
best part about this trading system is
that it makes a killing during a crisis
or recession. For example, during the
dot-com bubble in 2000, the 2008
financial crisis, the Russia-Ukraine
war, this periods like this is where
this trading system really shine. This
means you will make massive profits
while other traders are ah, losing their
pants. So, if you're interested, right,
then let's get to it because I will
explain to you the exact trading rules,
the entry, the exits, the chart
examples, and much more. So, let's get
started. So, trend following, what is
it? So, this is a trading strategy that
originated from the futures market. So,
this is why it's called futures trend
following. And it's used by
famous traders, you know, the total
traders, guess what? They are trend
followers. Market wizards like Ed
Seykota
and I don't know who who else I have
read a number of them, right? They all
are trend followers as well. So, this
trading strategy yes been around for a
long time
and
it's
proven to work and there's a good chance
it will continue working for the
foreseeable future. So, this is a
strategy that
allows you to write trends across
different asset classes. You can profit
in bull and bear markets because you
will go long and short. And you're
trading different asset classes like
indices, bonds, currency, metals, soft
commodities, etc. So, this is actually
one of the secret sauce, yeah? So, let
me just walk you through the concepts
behind this strategy. So, number one,
you want to be trading as many markets
as possible because it increases the
odds of you capturing a trend. So,
earlier I've shared with you the
different types of markets we trade and
of course
I share with you over here
are the different types of markets. Like
currencies itself is not one market. You
can have multiple currency pairs, euro
dollar, pound dollar, Aussie dollar,
blah blah blah, right? Maybe even 10 or
more. Same for metals, you have gold,
silver, copper, etc. So, you can see
that all these different asset classes
will give you many
markets to trade off.
And like I've said earlier, we are
pretty much going to buy markets that
are in an uptrend. Uptrend, we go long
in an uptrend and we go short in a
downtrend. And we will ride the trend
till it ends. And the reason, or rather
the way we ride a trend is using this
thing called TSL, a trailing stop loss.
And again, later on I'll share with you
the indicators that you can use on
TradingView to execute it.
So,
let's talk about the trend following
system that you're about to learn. So,
as mentioned, we are trading across
different markets. So, these are the
specific markets
that I've put over here that will be
used, right, for the backtest later
backtest later on. So, currencies, we
have pound dollar, dollar yen, Aussie
dollar, euro dollar, dollar against the
Chinese yen. So, I'm not going to go
through them. You can you can read it
for for yourself. Time frame is the
daily time frame and our risk management
is 2%. So, what this means is that when
we put on a trade and even if the trade
goes against us, we'll lose
about 2% if it hits our trailing stop
loss. It's not guaranteed 2% because
we are trading on a daily time frame and
we think we are waiting for the candle
to close. So, sometimes the loss might
be a little bit more, maybe 2.2, 2.3,
2.4, 2.5%. It is possible, but it
doesn't happen often. So, these are the
the parameters that I'll be using for
backtest later on.
Now, let's have a look at the rules of
this trading system. It's really, really
complicated. So, brace yourself. You
ready? Let's go.
Ta-da! That's it.
Just two lines, yeah? So, to go long, we
will simply go long when the price
closes the highest over the last 200
days. So, simply
put, right, we are looking for the
highest closing price over the last 200
days. If the market makes the highest
closing price over the last 200 days, we
go long. And we have a 6 ATR trailing
stop loss. ATR stands for average true
range. This is a volatility-based
trailing stop loss.
And to show you how this looks like on
the chart, it will look something like
this. Let's say the market goes up,
comes down, and let's say this is the
highest price point over the last
let's say this is the
over the last 200 days. If the market
goes up and it breaks out, we go long.
Let's call it L. And we ride the trend
till it starts to reverse and then over
here we sell, thereby allowing us to
capture the meat of the move. Let's call
this MOM, not mom, but the meat of the
move. So, that's the idea behind trend
following and this is a long example. A
short example is just the inverse. We go
short on the breakdown when there's a
lowest close over the last 200 days. So,
something like this closes below
the lowest closing price over the last
200 days, we go short, we ride the trend
down till it ends. Over here, let's say
it reverse and we buy back over here.
So, thereby allowing us to to again
capture the the meat of the move over
here. So, this is in essence what
futures trend following is about.
And what about a trailing stop loss?
Well, how do we know when exactly to you
know exit the trade? So, this is where
I'm going to walk you through a few
examples so you can see this in action.
Now, let's have a look at
some examples, shall we?
So, the first one is a trading setup on
coffee.
Okay, and couple of indicators that you
will find it useful. Let me show you the
first one. The first one over here you
can see is the Donchian channel, but
this one is actually modified to plot
the closing price.
So, where do you find this? I actually
developed this one myself using a
using an AI. So, just look for Donchian
channel and this one is called you can
you will be able to find this one
bracket closing price. So, that's the
one I'm using. Okay, and it looks
something like this. The settings over
here, just change these to 200 and you
should have something that looks
something like this. So, if I just they
should be quite simple. Donchian channel
closing, let's see what pops up.
Oh, there you have it, right? Well, my
name here anyway.
Yeah, so this is the one. Okay, so I'm
just going to remove the extra one.
There you have it. So, feel free to use
that.
And
next thing is okay, so you look at it at
this point, you can see that this
market, coffee,
we're waiting for a
setup and entry trigger to go long. So,
when the price touches this blue line.
So, this blue line over here demarcates
or highlights the highest closing price
over the last 200 days. So, if it closes
into this blue line over here, it's an
entry trigger to go long. So, what
happened next is kaput. There we have
it. This candle, the market has closed,
right? It's now at this point it's now
closed the highest over the last 200
days. And since now it it can only be
confirmed after the market has closed,
you can't trade after the close unless
you want to do after market hours, don't
recommend it. Wait for the next trading
day to open and then you trade it.
So, put, right? Next day, market open
over here and that's where you go long.
Right, this opening price you go long.
Now, the question is how do you then
trail your stop loss? So, this is where
the second indicator comes into play.
This is a Chandelier exit.
Okay, so if you want to look for it, I
think you can just go to TradingView.
I believe I use this one from this one
version Chandelier exit, yeah? This is
the one I used. Yeah, they have it,
looks similar. I'll remove the
duplicate. And the settings are over
here, 6 ATR and 20 period. Click okay
and there you have it. You have this
green line that pops up at the bottom.
So, what you're going to do is to trail
your stop loss. So, when the when this
market closes, let's say suddenly
reverse and closes below this green
line, okay?
You exit the trade because your trailing
stop loss is hit. It has hit 6 ATR
trailing stop loss. So, in this case,
let me just fast forward.
Okay, so I I this one I have to be
honest, I cherry-picked this chart to
show you how it's like riding a trend.
Looks easy on the chart, but remember
this is a daily time frame. You have to
endure all this ebb and flow of the
market, you know, you can see it breaks
out, it makes a pullback, almost hitting
your stop loss. You still got to hold
this trade, you know? And then
eventually breaks out higher, makes
another pullback, heads up higher.
Again, almost hitting your trading stop
loss and then go kaboom!
So, that's the the nature of trend
following. There's a lot of a
battle of your emotions, if you ask me,
especially those of you who are new to
trading. This is a strategy that again,
not most new traders is able to handle,
honestly speaking. Okay, then you can
see over here. Let's see when it when
does it break below the trailing Oh,
there you go, here. Finally, on this
candle over here, the market breaks and
close below your trailing stop loss,
which is over here. And since the market
is closed, you can't exit. So, your
earliest exit will be on this candle
over here at this opening price. This is
where you sell this position for a nice
profit. Okay, so this is how the futures
trend following system look like. So,
and there you have it, right? This is
the idea behind
futures trend following.
And now, since our rules are objective,
we can look at the results over the last
25 years.
So, you can see over here, this is the
equity curve I shared with you earlier
and month on month, year on year, this
is where it's important. Have a look.
So, you can see that
as a trend follower, you're not going to
make money every month or every year. I
think same goes for all trading
strategies. Nothing works all the time.
But what's remarkable about trend
following, in particular futures trend
following, is that during a crisis
period, during a recession,
when the stock market is taking a
beating, this strategy usually does
well. You can see in 2000 with the
dot-com bubble, up 22%. 2008 financial
crisis, up 65% for this system.
2020 with COVID, up 8%. Not not not
huge. 2022 Russia-Ukraine war, up 25 or
rather 56%. So, you can see that this is
a system that thrives during difficult
market environment.
And if you look at the
metrics,
total return 2,864 since 2000. So,
annualized basis is about 14% annual
return. Your winning rate is about 45%.
You can see that it's less than half.
So, you're actually losing more than
half the time or rather you're losing
more than half the time. Yeah, correct.
You're losing 54% of the time to be
exact. Your payoff ratio is 1.74. So,
you can see that
on average, your gains are
larger.
Pretty large, right? Relative to your
average losses. And your maximum
drawdown in this system is pretty steep,
37% and it's not
out of the norm, right? To see drawdown
exceeding 40, 50, or even 60%. So, there
are trend-following hedge funds.
They have maximum drawdown of, you know,
in excess of 50% and that's really the
cost of being a trend follower. The
drawdowns are not fun to go through.
It's painful. It will test your
emotions. It will test your
resilience. In fact, let me just
go back to let's see.
All right. I have all this data exported
on Excel. So, you can see over here
there's all this data exported. You can
see that as a trend follower, there are
periods where you just have to kind of
like suck it up, right? You can see over
here since over here made a new high and
then kind of like, you know, drawdown
for the next few years over here.
Same thing for this, made a new high
over here and then it took a drawdown
for a few years. It might look short on
this chart, but this is like a few
years. It's not like few weeks or few
months. So, as a trend follower, your
winning rate is low as well as, you
know, you have to be able to endure this
lengthy drawdowns.
So, pros and cons of future trend
following is future trend following is
number one, there is no correlation to
the stock market. So, this is a good
thing for those of you who are, let's
say, stock investors, stock traders, you
want a system or strategy that is
diversified. Futures trend following is
something worth considering because
later on I'll explain, you know, why
this is the case. This usually does well
in the bear market as you've seen
earlier.
The downside to this is that this
system, this strategy has a low winning
rate. Generally, trend followers
winning rate are between 30 to 45% and
it's difficult for most traders
psychology, especially if this is the
only trading system that you trade.
It's really going to test your
your heart and soul.
Okay? So, but that's it. There are
things that you can do to kind of
alleviate this this pain, especially if
you have multiple trading systems or if,
let's say, you
uh
long the stock market, you could be an
investor, a growth investor, a value
investor. If the stock market is
bullish, your stock investments are
likely to make money.
And trend following, maybe the period
doesn't make or do it that well, doesn't
matter. At least your stock investments
or stock trading is, you know, providing
cushion for it. At the same time, when
markets are bad, when your stock
investment portfolio take a hit, guess
what? Trend following will shine in. So,
this means that your losses from your
stock investment will not be as painful
because you have trend following. Make
sense?
Now, before you go, I'd like you to get
access to this free training. You can
get it at tradingwithrayner.com/go
or in the description or in the comment
section below this video. So, in this
training, you will discover three
rule-based trading strategies that work
and they're all backed by data. In fact,
the strategy that you've just learned is
actually taken from this training. So,
you will learn
in other words, two more extra trading
strategies. And again, I'll walk you
through the
trading rules, the entries, the exits,
the risk management, and chart examples
so you can quickly understand the
concepts of these strategies. And that's
not all because I would also like to
give you
the PDF slides of this training, the
trading strategies cheat sheets so you
can quickly recap the rules of this
different trading system, and the
backtest report of all these different
trading systems so you can see the
winning rate, the losing rate, what is
the payoff ratio, etc. All the backtest
report given to you in this training for
free. So, everything is free over here.
Just go down to tradingwithrayner.com/go
or I'll put the link somewhere in the
description below or in the comment
section below. Just click on it, you
come to this page and you can get
started immediately. So, with that said,
I wish you good luck, good trading. I
will
talk to you soon.